hey guys I'm crystal West and today
we're going to talk about the Birmingham
Children's much Cheers grizzle let's
March
delicious
alright so where is her story began who
knows so her story begins in 1963 and
Alabama where racism is so deeply
embedded in the community but the
breaking point for Gwendolyn Sanders was
when she realized in the seventh grade
that her textbook had previously news by
a white fifth grader she's like I knew I
wasn't allowed to go to the same movie
theaters and like that as white
people but y'all are giving us raggedy
old textbooks that you are giving your
fifth graders like not only do you not
give about me or my people you don't
give about my education either
and so she realized them and things
needed to change and she wanted to be a
part of it
so around the time that this story shot
starts charts and shirley chart so
around the same time my mother King jr.
was urging the newly elected President
Kennedy like man we need some official
legislation to stop the that's
happening to black people like you need
to get involved in the President and
Kennedy sympathized he was like you know
I agree with you but the party is still
made up of poor white southern voters
and I cannot
alienate them which was about sounds
familiar and kind of distressing right
so dr. King is using the 16th Street
Baptist Church to try to organize
protests and Monda came in like you know
throw to stop us to do something and the
adults were like listen it's not that we
don't agree with you but at
end of the day I still have to put food
on table and pay the rent in this hole
I don't want them burning crosses on my
lawn or any like that so like
not safe we can't do this and
dr. King was like if we can't enact
change in Birmingham we can't do it
anywhere who can join in the protest and
get arrested with us and he was sort of
shocked to see
Gwendolyn Sanders and her sisters get up
and say you know what we'll do it we
will do something about this and then
more and more kids stood up to violence
here they decided to mobilize so that's
exactly what they did they went back to
school like listen we know y'all was
sick of the racism and there's something
we can actually do about it
and on May 2nd they the protest went
down administrators started locking the
doors to keep them from getting out and
kids were just straight up jump out the
window like bitching I don't keep us
here over a thousand kids left school to
go to Kelly Ingram Park to protest but
then will Connor head of the Birmingham
Police Department it's like okay we all
black asses can go to jail so they
started carding these kids off by the
dozens and over a thousand kids were
arrested on that first day which is
insane after a few days of protest the
Birmingham jail with Thole overcrowding
and
more kids are arrested others come back
now to take up their place but on May
5th that was where she got really real
cool Bull Connor was looking at hundreds
of black kids standing up to his
his life let's bring out the
hoses these are high pressure knock you
the water hoses but the kids realized
their strength in numbers and
togetherness matters so those kids
linked hands and said not today
not today
so Bull Connor decides okay release the
k-9 units so that the dogs could these
kids up and at this point there were
news crews there that caught the entire
situation on camera and these are now
some of the most infamous shots of the
civil rights movement and after people
saw children on international TV being
sprayed with hoses and attacked by dogs
a mind shift occurred and after eight
solid days of protests President Kennedy
felt motivated to come out and say you
know what I didn't want to say before
because of the southern way of odors but
their mothers are racist so it's time to
just be really the that you are
going out here and doing to people in my
name is not the okay man I love drinking
[Laughter]
so anyway about the kids well after the
success of the Birmingham Children's
March dr. King decided to ride that
momentum and he gave his I have a dream
speech Bull Connor was fired
and the Civil Rights Act was passed
within a year of all that so it was
monumental that Gwendolyn Sanders and
these kids weren't willing to say this
is not a game and you won't
treat us in our people this way because
we're here and this is what's going on
and it's time for us to stand up too and
so I don't have to worry about that sort
of thing the way those kids even did or
their parents even did no I don't take
that for granted cheers as a kid you see
the kids all right
this is gone I'm not a no no
more
[Music]
you